Guide to the Berj Aprahamian photograph collection AD.MC.157
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Berj Aprahamian photograph collection
1966-1980
1967-1969
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Aprahamian, Berj, 1931-
AD.MC.157
246 Photographic Slides housed in 14 folders in one box, 0.20 linear feet
326 Photographic Prints in two boxes, 2.8 linear feet
3.0 Linear Feet in 3 boxes.
Color photographic slides and prints, containing scenes in the city and emirate of Abu Dhabi, that depict scenery, prominent buildings, and the construction of the city's infrastructure, including the first seawall and Corniche, dating chiefly from the late 1960s.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for use in the Reading Room of the Archives and Special Collections department of the NYU Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate source of acquisition
Acquired from Berj Aprahamian, August 2025.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series, according to format: slides and prints. Within those, the slides are arranged in roughly chronological order (where dates are present), while the prints are arranged in categories by topic, using descriptive terms and groupings either devised by the creator of the collection, or adapted from those by the processing archivist.
Biographical note
Berj Aprahamian was born in Jerusalem in 1931, where his family lived in the Armenian Quarter. As a child he attended Armenian elementary schools, but his secondary schooling was interrupted due to the Arab-Israeli war of 1947, when Jerusalem was partitioned and he could no longer reach his school. Although he eventually completed his secondary schooling, this forced absence led him to work as a temporary accounting clerk with the British authorities in Palestine. His brother later found him a position as an accountant with a construction firm in Iraq, and working in this environment exposed him to the work of engineers, a field that he developed an interest in. He began studying engineering at Aleppo College in Syria, but after his first year there, he transferred to Roberts College in Istanbul, where he completed his bachelor's degree in Civil Engineering in 1957.
Following his graduation, he returned to Iraq, working with Shaheen and Janabi Contractors as an assistant resident engineer in Kirkuk, but moved to Kuwait in 1958, where he was employed by that country's Ministry of Public Works. In October 1966 he moved to Abu Dhabi, in the Trucial States, where he joined the British construction firm Arabicon. One of the early projects he worked on was the construction of Abu Dhabi's first seawall along what is now that city's Corniche. Aprahamian accompanied the Emirate's ruler, Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al Nahyan, when the latter attended the ribbon cutting for this project in June 1967, explaining to him the work of dredging, land reclamation, and the sheet piling necessary to build this structure. In 1969 Aprahamian joined the firm of Brook and Khalfan, eventually rising to the level of General Manager, and supervising a variety of infrastructure projects in the city and emirate of Abu Dhabi, ranging from highway construction to the building of the breakwater in 1973, a structure that has led to the development of the Marina district of Abu Dhabi. In 1984 he became a partner in the firm of Spectrum Engineering Consultants in Abu Dhabi.
A year after his arrival in Abu Dhabi, Aprahamian's wife, Suzanne, joined him there, and they raised their two daughters in Abu Dhabi. Aprahamian became an active member of the city's growing Armenian community, where he was instrumental in efforts to establish an Armenian school in the 1970s and later the design and construction of the Armenian Embassy in 2007. He was later active in the Armenian Cultural Association, serving as its honorary chair from 1992 until the dissolution of that group in 2010.
In 2018, at the urging of Sheikh Nahyan bin Mubarak al Nahyan, Aprahamian published a selection of his early photographs of Abu Dhabi in a book dedicated to Sheikh Zayed, and titled "A Tribute with Love: in Memory of Sheikh Zayed Bin Sultan Al Nahyan," in which Sheikh Nahyan provided the foreword.
Berj Aprahamian died at his home in Abu Dhabi on 18 November 2025.
[Source: adapted from the article "The Legacy of Berj Aprahamian," by Hrach Kalsahakian," published February 6, 2024 on the website "Azad-Hye," https://www.azad-hye.com/the-legacy-of-berj-aprahamian/, accessed July 2025, as well as information from family members.]
Content Description
The Berj Aprahamian collection consists of color photographic slides and prints, containing scenes of the city and emirate of Abu Dhabi that depict scenery, prominent buildings, and the construction of the city's infrastructure, including the first seawall and Corniche, dating chiefly from the late 1960s.
The earliest images date from November and December 1966, just a couple of months after Aprahamian's arrival in Abu Dhabi, while the bulk of the images appeared to have been captured between early 1967 and late 1968. The subject matter of his photographs includes scenes of daily life in the city of Abu Dhabi during this period, as well as images more directly related to his work as a civil engineer on projects related to the drive to modernize the city's infrastructure under the rule of Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al-Nahyan. Related to this latter area are images of newly constructed roads, the laying of pipelines, the demolition of older buildings in the center of town, and most notably, the construction of the first seawall along the city's waterfront, including photographs of the work as it progressed, as well as a ceremony at the inauguration of this project, at which Sheikh Zayed was present, in June 1967. The city's changing coastline is a frequent theme in these photographs, with images showing the buildings along the waterfront from various vantage points, goods being unloaded from boats docked at the city's first jetty and port, the effects of coastal flooding, and images of the city as seen from offshore, taken during an engineering survey.
As a new arrival, Aprahamian was also interested in the daily lives of the city's inhabitants and the general surroundings, and documented many different facets of Abu Dhabi, including the old central market (or souq), the city's main street (corresponding roughly with modern-day Sheikh Rashid bin Saeed Road), local inhabitants, and in August 1967, the first Accession Day parade, marking the anniversary of Sheikh Zayed's accession as ruler of the Emirate of Abu Dhabi. Also depicted are notable landmarks, such as the first airport terminal and airstrip, used by Gulf Airways (at the site of present-day Al Bateen Executive Airport), the dedication of the Al Khubairat School, which both of Aprahamian's daughters attended, and the first Christian churches in the city. Both the school and the churches were located adjacent to the coastal road that would later be known as the Corniche, but were subsequently moved inland, to the Mushrif district, in the 1980s.
While most of this collection documents the city of Abu Dhabi, a smaller number of images from this period also show portions of the city of Al-'Ain and nearby landscape, including Jebel Hafit, as well as a trip to the emirate of 'Ajman.
The photographs in this collection were initially developed as color photographic slides, many of which were later reproduced as large format photographic prints. As a result, many of the prints duplicate the content of the slides, however, not all of them do.
Abū Ẓaby (United Arab Emirates); Abū Ẓaby (United Arab Emirates) -- Social life and customs.
- Photographic prints
  - Abu Dhabi: Abu Dhabi Petroleum Company (ADPC) building (2 prints), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abu Dhabi: Accession Day celebration (10 prints), August 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Abu Dhabi: aerial views (11 prints), 1968 and undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Abu Dhabi: airport (8 prints), August 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Abu Dhabi: Al Hosn fort (Qasr al-Hosn)(18 prints), 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Abu Dhabi: Al Khubeirat School inaguration, with Sheikh Zayed (6 prints), April 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Abu Dhabi: Al Khubeirat School, nativity program (4 prints), January 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Abu Dhabi: Bateen Beach (4 prints, including one with Aprahamian and colleagues), January - April 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Abu Dhabi: demolition of old buildings (9 prints), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Abu Dhabi: digging for aggregate, Jern Yafoor (Baniyas)(6 prints), undated, circa 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Abu Dhabi: first churches constructed (Anglican and Catholic) (3 prints, one from Vahan Piranian), 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Abu Dhabi: Khor al-Maqta, causeway and bridge (10 prints), 1967-1968 and undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Abu Dhabi: main street and square (8 prints), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Abu Dhabi: merchandise in old port (6 prints), May 1967 - July 1968, and undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Abu Dhabi: military parade on Accession Day (12 prints), August 1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Abu Dhabi: miscellaneous, people and scenery (17 prints), 1966-1967, and undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Abu Dhabi: miscellaneous old buildings (8 prints), undated, circa 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Abu Dhabi: old housing (9 prints), 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Abu Dhabi: old mosque (3 prints), 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Abu Dhabi: old souk (21 prints), March 1967 - May 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Abu Dhabi: pipeline project (2 prints), undated, circa 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Abu Dhabi: port and jetty (6 prints), 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Abu Dhabi: roads under construction (5 prints), 1968 and undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Abu Dhabi: sea front (future Corniche)(16 prints), 1967-1968, and undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Abu Dhabi: seawall project, opening ceremony (28 prints), 1967, either June or July (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Abu Dhabi: various buildings (16 prints), 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Abu Dhabi: views at sunset (4 prints), May - July 1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Abu Dhabi: views from the sea (6 prints), May - June 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Abu Dhabi: water wells (3 prints), November 1966 and undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Abu Dhabi: wedding scenes at residence of Sheikh Hamdan bin Mohammed (13 prints), undated, circa late 1960s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Al 'Ain: aerial views of town, and images of Al Jahili fort (9 prints), March 1967 - May 1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Al 'Ain: falaj (aflaj) in Al 'Ain (2 prints), undated, circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Al 'Ain: Scenes in al 'Ain (14 prints), 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Al 'Ain: Sheikh Zayed's residence (Al 'Ain Palace)(2 prints), 1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Das Island, including aerial views (11 prints), April - November 1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - General: a trip in the Emirates (Ajman) with 'Abdallah (chief driver of Six Construction)(4 prints), March 1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - General: sand rock formations on road to Al 'Ain (12 prints), February - June 1967 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Jebel Hafeet rock formations (2 prints), April 1972 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Photographic slides
  - 1966 (December) and 1967 (general) (15 slides) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1967: February - April (20 slides) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1967: May - June (20 slides) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1967: July - August (20 slides) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1968: January - May (20 slides) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1968: May - August (14 slides) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1968: November, and undated (16 slides) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Undated, circa 1967-1968: various scenes in Abu Dhabi, including Khor al-Maqta (18 slides) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Undated, circa 1967-1968: Qasr al-Hosn and surroundings (20 slides) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Undated, circa 19678-1968: Abu Dhabi, town center and waterfront (20 slides) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Undated, circa 1967-1968: Abu Dhabi, wedding celebration and old souq (15 slides) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Undated, circa 1967-1968: people, including Hugh Boustead, Ahmed Khalifa al-Suwaidi (6 slides) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Undated, circa 1967-1968: Abu Dhabi, general views and buildings (23 slides) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - March 1980 and undated, circa late 1970s (18 slides) (Box 3, Folder 14)